Guide to the Hispanic Women in Leadership Records
University of Houston Libraries
Hispanic Women in Leadership Records
1977-2000
1987-2000
1999-007
Hispanic Women in Leadership
8.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The Hispanic Women in Leadership collection contains information about the group's conferences, meetings, organization, and programs. The conferences series is the largest, as the annual conference is the main activity of Hispanic Women.
Historical Note:
The idea for a Hispanic women's leadership group originated in 1987, when a small group of Hispanic women in Houston planned a women's conference. The Hispanic Women's Leadership Conference Committee's March conference, held in conjunction with the YWCA, was a success. In June 1988, Hispanic Women in Leadership was formed as a separate, nonprofit, tax exempt organization. The organization has grown from the approximately twenty original members to over two hundred, the majority of whom are professional Hispanic women. Members include doctors, lawyers, accountants, educators, media representatives and other professionals who provide positive role models to women and girls.
Hispanic Women in Leadership's main goal is to promote leadership skills among Hispanic women in Houston. In conjunction with this goal, the organization promotes education of Hispanic women and girls, identifies successful role models, develops a network of professional women, and encourages Hispanic women to embrace and celebrate their cultural heritage.
Hispanic Women in Leadership's major activity is their annual conference, held each spring in Houston. These conferences, which have grown over the years, have themes relevant to Hispanic women. They feature local and national educators and professional women and men who present workshops on issues such as the glass ceiling in the workplace and child care. The conferences raise money for scholarships to deserving young Hispanic women. In addition to the annual conference, Hispanic Women in Leadership also sponsors other fundraisers, such as fashion shows and garage sales.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Hispanic Women in Leadership
Genre/Form of Material:
Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Records (documents); Videocassettes
Topical Term:
Hispanic American women -- Texas -- Houston; Hispanic Americans -- Texas -- Houston; Women -- Societies and clubs -- Texas -- Houston
Acquisition Information:
Original donations by Hispanic Women in Leadership, 1999-2000. Accession #2016-029. 2 boxes of unprocessed material donated in 2016
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Hispanic Women in Leadership collection contains information about the group's conferences, meetings, organization, and programs. The conferences series is the largest, as the annual conference is the main activity of Hispanic Women. The group organized their papers in three-ring binders, but in order to facilitate access to the collection, the material has for the most part been re-arranged chronologically in broad series such as administrative, correspondence, and conferences, and then further divided into sub-series. For preservation reasons, facsimiles on thermofax paper and newspaper articles have been copied onto regular paper, and newspapers have been placed in a separate oversize box.
Two boxes of unprocessed material were donated in 2016 and are identified as Accession #2016-029.
Detailed List of Contents
- Administrative, 1988-2000
  Scope and Contents
  The Administrative series contains the papers pertaining to the administration of Hispanic Women in Leadership from the organization's inception in 1988 through 2000. The series is divided into three sub-series, Organizational, President, and Secretary. The Organizational subseries contains three folders, dating from 1988 to 2000. They contain basic information on the group's history, organization, and leadership. The President sub-series contains six folders, dating from 1989 to 1999, and includes mainly financial records. The Secretary sub-series contains nineteen folders, dating from 1988 to 1999. This sub-series contains items such as agendas and minutes of board and general meetings, calendars, membership information, newsletters, and news clippings. A separation sheet in the folder indicates if a newspaper has been removed to the oversize box. The material in both the President and Secretary sub-series is arranged chronologically. In order to facilitate access, the material in the President and Secretary sub-series has been significantly re-arranged and a new order imposed. Hispanic Women in Leadership used binders to arrange the majority of the papers in the Administrative series. Each officer, at the beginning of their term of office, was given a binder for their papers. Some of the binders were better organized than others, and some of the binders for a particular officer or year were missing. There was also a lot of duplication of papers. To create a consistent and clear arrangement, the material has been divided functionally between the offices of president and secretary. These were the only consistent binders, and many of the papers in other binders, such as vice-president, were also found in the president or secretary binders.
  - Organizational
    - Mission Statement/History, 1988-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Constitution/By-Laws, 1988-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Board of Directors, 1991-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - President
    - Financial, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Financial, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Financial, 1997-2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Annual Report, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Legal Considerations, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Training/Education, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Secretary
    - Meetings, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Meetings, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Meetings, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Meetings, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Meetings, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Meetings, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Membership, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Membership, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Membership, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Membership, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Membership, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Membership, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Blank Forms, 1989-1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Calendars, 1991-1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Hall of Fame, 1989-1999 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Letterhead/Stationery, 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - News Clippings, 1988-1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Newsletters, 1989-2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Robert's Rules of Order, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1988-2000
  This series contains nine folders, dating from 1988 to 2000. The material is arranged chronologically, not by writer or recipient. It does not include correspondence relating to conferences, which is in the conferences series.
  - 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1994 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1995 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1997 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1998 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Conferences, 1988-2000
  This series contains ninety folders and comprises the bulk of the material in the Hispanic Women in Leadership collection. The materials date from 1988 to 2000. This series is arranged chronologically, and within each year, items have been divided, in general, into ten subjects. These ten subjects were common to most of the conferences except the early ones. As time went on, the annual conference became larger and more elaborate. The earliest conferences therefore do not contain as much material or as many subjects as more recent conferences The subjects are conference committees, correspondence, evaluations, exhibitors, financial, hotel, program, public relations/publicity, registration, and speakers. They are arranged alphabetically. The 2000 conference correspondence folder includes a letter from Texas Governor George W. Bush congratulating Hispanic Women in Leadership on a successful conference.
  - Program, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Conference Committees, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Exhibitors, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Financial, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Program, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Conference Committees, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Evaluations, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Exhibitors, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Program, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Registration, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Speakers, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Conference Committees, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Exhibitors, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Financial, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Program, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Public Relations/Publicity, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Registration, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Speakers, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Conference Committees, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Exhibitors, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Financial, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Hotel, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Program, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Speakers, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Public Relations/Publicity, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Conference Committees, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Evaluations, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Exhibitors, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Financial, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Program, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Registration, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Speakers, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Conference Committees, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Evaluations, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10-12)
  - Exhibitors, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Financial, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Program, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Public Relations/Publicity, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Registration, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Speakers, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Conference Committees, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Exhibitors, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Financial, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Hotel, 1994-1995 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Program, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Public Relations/Publicity, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Registration, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Speakers, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Conference Committees, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Evaluations, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Exhibitors, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Financial, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Hotel, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Program, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Public Relations/Publicity, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Registration, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Speakers/Entertainment, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Conference Committees, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Exhibitors, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Financial, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Hotel, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Program, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Registration, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Public Relations/Publicity, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Speakers/Entertainment, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Conference Committees, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Financial, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Hotel, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Program, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Public Relations/Publicity, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Registration, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Speakers/Entertainment, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Conference Committees, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1998-1999 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Financial, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Program, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Scholarships, 1992-1999
  This series contains thirteen folders, dating from 1992 to 1999. The majority of this series is scholarship applications from 1992 and 1993, with some correspondence specifically related to the scholarships. For privacy reasons, transcripts of students applying for scholarships have been removed and destroyed. The applications are arranged alphabetically and then chronologically, and the correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - Applications - A-L, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Applications - M-Z, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Applications - A-D, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Applications - F-G, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Applications - H-Mc, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Applications - Me-R, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Applications - S-Z, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1995-1999 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Scholarship Committees, 1992-1999 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Awards, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Blank Applications, 1992-1999 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Judges' Tally Sheets, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Activities, 1988-1999
  This series contains seventeen folders, dating from 1988 to 1999. The material includes information about activities other than the annual conferences, such as fashion shows, art exhibits, and garage sales. The material is arranged chronologically.
  - 1988-1989 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 1992 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - 1993 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Young Hispanas, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - 1994 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - 1995 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - 1996 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - 1997 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - 1998 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - 1999 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Invitations to Non-HWL Activities, 1991-1999 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Photographs - Hall of Fame, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Photographs - Hall of Fame, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Photographs, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 20-21)
  - Photographs, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
  - Photographs, 1998 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Outside Organizations, 1977-1999
  This series contains thirteen folders, dating from 1977 to 1999 and consists of material about organizations other than Hispanic Women in Leadership, but which are of interest to the group. The material is arranged alphabetically by the name of the organization.
  - A-F, 1990-1996 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - H-Hi, 1989-1992 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Houston Area Women's Shelter, 1977-1997 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Ho-Mc, 1989-1999 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Mujer a Mujer (Sisters of Charity Health Care System), 1992 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Mus-Tenneco, 1990-1993 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Texano-Correspondence, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Texano-Facsimile Numbers, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Texano-Newsletters, 1993-1995 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Texano-Notes and Tidbits, 1989, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Te-United, 1994-1998 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - United Way, 1991-1995 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Wh-Z, 1990-1999 (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Ephemera
  This series contains five items, a cloth book bag with the logo of the Hispanic Women's Conference Committee, a pen from Rice University, a satchel with the logo of Hispanic Women in Leadership, and two videotapes of awards presentations at the 1998 and 2000 conferences. Other than the videotapes, none of the items in this series are dated. The videotapes are shelved with the collection next to box 10.
  - Cloth Book Bag, undated (Box 11, Item 1)
  - Rice University Pen, undated (Box 11, Item 2)
  - Satchel, undated (Box 11, Item 3)
  - Videotape - Hispanic Women in Leadership Hall of Fame, 1998 (Item 1)
  - Videotape - Hispanic Women in Leadership Award to Ninfa Lorenzo, 2000 (Item 2)
- Oversize
  This series contains newspapers and newspaper articles dating from 1988 to 2000. They were removed and placed in an oversize box for preservation reasons. Separation sheets in the folders refer the researcher to the oversize box. This series also contains two large, framed proclamations, both dated 2000. One is from the office of Houston Mayor Lee P. Brown, and the other is from the office of Stafford Mayor Leonard Scarcella; both are in honor of Hispanic Women in Leadership.
  - Newspaper Articles, 1988-1999 (Ovs box 11, Ovs item 1)
  - Proclamation from Houston Mayor, 2000 (Ovs box 11, Ovs item 2)
  - Proclamation from Stafford Mayor, 2000 (Ovs box 11, Ovs item 3)
- Unprocessed additions
  Accession #2016-029. 2 boxes of unprocessed material donated in 2016. Contact the curator with questions regarding access to this material.